Okay good morning. We're
on today's דף מ"ג, Daf Mem Gimmel, 43. We are at the
top of the page. We were talking
about where סקילה Skilah happens. The משנה Mishnah said that once the
דין din is finished, once someone's judgment is finished and he is
sentenced to death, you take him חוץ לבית דין, chutz l'Beit Din,
you take him outside the בית דין, Beit Din, which the
גמרא Gemara I believe will talk about. I don't think it's talked
about yet, like what does that actually mean?
And we talked yesterday about thanks to Michal's lovely drawing here where
that happens. You have the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash משכן Mishkan in
the desert,
מחנה הלווים Machaneh haLeviyim here, and then the מחנה ישראל Machaneh Yisrael
here, and outside of all of them is where the סקילה Skilah
happens.
On the אבן החיצון.
avan hachitzon. What's the stone? That's where the stones are. Great. Or
possibly one stone which we're going to cover today.
So what we finished off with: ובני ישראל עשו כאשר צוה ה',
u-venei Yisrael asu ka'asher
tziva Hashem, which לכסותו היי מיבעי ליה, l'kisuto hai mibayei lei, I'm
actually going to go back a little bit because the thought continues.
So we're going to go from after on the bottom of מ"ב
עמוד ב', Mem Beit Amud Beit, after מכשיר ממכשיר עדיף ליה, makshir
mimakshir adis lei, and רב פפא. Rav Pappa. Yep. Okay. רב פפא
אמר. Rav Pappa amar. So רב פפא Rav Pappa is going to
cite an alternative source for how we know that סקילה Skilah happens
outside of all the camps. רב פפא אמר. Rav Pappa amar. משה
היכא הוה יתיב? Moshe heicha hava yativ? Where was משה Moshe hang
out? Where did משה Moshe sit? במחנה לוייה. b'Machaneh Leviyah. In this
second circle here. That's where משה Moshe lived.
Or at least where he was when he talked to God in
this case. ואמר ליה רחמנא, va-amar lei Rachmana, and God said to
him, הוצא את המקלל אל מחוץ למחנה. hotzei et hamikallel el michutz
lamachaneh.
מחוץ למחנה לוייה. michutz lamachaneh Leviyah. So from where משה Moshe was
sitting when God said take this מקלל, mikallel, take the person who
cursed God's name out of the camp, what משה Moshe heard was
great, I'll take him out of the camp that I am sitting
in, which means taking him out to מחנה ישראל. Machaneh Yisrael.
ויוציאו את המקלל אל מחוץ למחנה, va-yotziu et hamikallel el michutz lamachaneh,
after they, after משה Moshe took him from מחנה לוייה Machaneh Leviyah
to מחנה ישראל, Machaneh Yisrael, then the rest of ישראל Yisrael take
him out מחוץ למחנה, michutz lamachaneh, which would be the מחנה Machaneh
he's currently in, which means going all the way outside the camps
and that's where he was
stoned. חוץ למחנה ישראל, chutz lamachaneh Yisrael, ויוציאו את המקלל אל מחוץ
למחנה. va-yotziu et hamikallel el michutz lamachaneh. חוץ למחנה ישראל היי מיבעי
ליה לעשייה. chutz lamachaneh Yisrael hai mibayei l'asiya. But how can we
learn from חוץ, chutz, ויוציאו את המקלל אל מחוץ למחנה? va-yotziu et
hamikallel el michutz lamachaneh? That's just telling us that it happened. It's
not telling us any new information. It's telling us that בני ישראל
Benei Yisrael actually took him outside of the camp like God told
משה, Moshe, and therefore we need that פסוק, pasuk, we can't learn
anything extra from it because we need it just to tell us
that it happened. Oh no, how do we know? There's another source
to know that it happened. עשייה בהדיא כתיבא, asiya bahedya ketiva, ובני
ישראל עשו כאשר צוה ה' את משה. u-venei Yisrael asu ka'asher tziva
Hashem et Moshe.
We have a פסוק pasuk that says בני ישראל Benei Yisrael did
that which God commanded them. Meaning,
that teaches us that they took him outside of the last מחנה.
Machaneh. Therefore that leaves us with this other פסוק pasuk ויוציאו את
המקלל אל מחוץ למחנה. va-yotziu et hamikallel el michutz lamachaneh. They took
the מקלל, mikallel, they took the curser outside of outside of מחנה
Machaneh to mean they took him outside of
מחנה ישראל. Machaneh Yisrael. דמצוה משמע. de-mitzva mashma. אלא מעתה, ela me'ata,
but if we learn from that פסוק pasuk that that's what happened,
וירגמו אותו אבן, מאי
עבדי ליה?
va-yirgamu oto even mai
abdi lei? And they stoned him with stones, what are we going
to do with that? Meaning, if all of the actions that God
commanded משה Moshe we learn that בני ישראל Benei Yisrael did from
this verse that says they did all the things that God commanded
משה, Moshe, this is another extra verse. This וירגמו
אותו באבן, va-yirgamu oto ba-even, and they stoned the מקלל mikallel with
stones is another extra verse because we already know they did it
because the תורה Torah tells us they did everything that God commanded
משה. Moshe. So וירגמו אותו אבן va-yirgamu oto even, מאי עבדי ליה?
mai abdi lei? What do we learn from that? הא מיבעי ליה
לכדתניא. ha mibayei liktedanya. That teaches us what we learn in this
following ברייתא. baraita. וירגמו אותו באבן, va-yirgamu oto ba-even,
אותו oto ולא בכסותו. v'lo be-kisuto. We learn from this you stone
him, they stone him, וירגמו
אותו באבן, va-yirgamu oto ba-even, they stone him with a stone, right,
אבן even is singular, that's going to be important. ולא
בכסותו, v'lo be-kisuto, and not while he is clothed. That we learn
from the word
אותו. oto. אבן, even,
שאם
מת באבן אחת יצא. she-im met b'even achat yatza. That if he
died after being struck with only one stone, you are still, you
have still fulfilled the obligation to stone this man.
ואיצטריך למיכתב v'itztrich l'michatav אבן, even, ואיצטריך למיכתב v'itztrich l'michatav אבנים. avanim.
We have in two different places where the תורה Torah describes stoning.
One place it says אבן even and one place it says
אבנים. avanim. Where does it
say אבנים avanim again?
I don't know David, do you have the...?
You should have אבנים avanim cited in there.
It's not in the... it's not in the traditional printing.
ויקרא Vayikra
oh wait, is it ורגמו אותו באבנים כל העדה? ve'ragmu oto ba'avanim
kol ha'edah? Something the same, במדבר, Bamidbar, yeah.
Yeah, that's the
מקושש עצים. Mekoshesh etzim. ואיצטריכא דכתב אבן ומכתב אבנים. ve'itztrichah de'ichtav even
u'michtav avanim. So why do we have both? דאי כתב רחמנא אבן
הוה אמינא היכא דלא מית בחדא לא ניתי אחריטא
ומקטליה.
de'ei katav Rachmana even hava amina heicha de'lo
meit be'chada lo neite achrita u'miktalei. I would have thought if it
only, if we only had our verse here that said ורגמוהו באבן,
ve'regamuhu ba'even, I would have thought that if he doesn't die after
he gets struck with the first
stone—by the way, the whole description of stoning is going to come
up later, what it actually looks like. It's not what... it's not
what we traditionally think of as stoning, unless you know and then
you do traditional...
anyway...
ומקטליה. u'miktalei. So you might think that if you took one stone
out and struck him with it and he didn't die, then you
don't... you don't bring another stone to stone him.
כתב רחמנא אבנים. Katav Rachmana avanim. That's why it says over there
in... where was it? In דברים? Devarim? In... sorry, in במדבר Bamidbar
stones plural. ואי כתב רחמנא אבנים, ve'ei katav Rachmana avanim, but if
we only had the place where it said אבנים, avanim, הוה אמינא
מעיקרא ניתי תרתי. hava amina mei'ikara neitei tartei. כתב רחמנא אבן. Katav
Rachmana even. So if it had said, if it had only said
אבנים, avanim, then I would have thought
מלכתחילה mil'chat'chilah a priori you would bring more than one stone. Therefore
we learn אבן even to learn, therefore the תורה Torah said אבן
even to learn that you do one first. If he doesn't die
then you use another stone, or I suppose as many stones as
you need until the person who is sentenced to death is quite
dead. מעיקרא ניתי תרתי כתב רחמנא אבן. mei'ikara neitei tartei katav Rachmana
even. Okay. והא האי תנא נאמר קאמר. veha hai tanna ne'emar ka'amar.
והא האי תנא נאמר. veha hai tanna ne'emar.
Why did... okay, so then the גמרא Gemara is going to ask...
if we go back to the bottom of מב עמוד ב, mem-bet
amud-bet, רב פפא Rav Pappa brings a source for how we know
that סקילה skilah happens outside the camp, but we had just already
learned it from...
from a Tannaitic source. מחוץ לשלש מחנות? me'chutz le'shalosh machanot? Yeah,
all of the גזירה שוות gezeirah shavot that we just did were
really Tannaitic, right? תניא בית הסקילה היה חוץ לשלש מחנות Tanya beit
ha'skilah hayah chutz le'shalosh machanot all the way to the beginning of
the גמרא Gemara after the משנה Mishnah there.
בגזירה שוה דדמי למקלל ולזובחי חוץ. be'gezeirah shavah de'deimi le'mikalel u'lezovechei chutz.
Right, this is the גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah between the מקלל mikalel
and פרים הנשרפים parim ha'nisrafim and between the מקלל mikalel and שוחטי
חוץ. shochutei chutz. In both... in all three cases it says מחוץ
למחנה. mi'chutz la'machaneh. Right, and that was Tannaitic.
So how come רב פפא Rav Pappa had to bring his own
source for סקילה skilah happening outside of the camp when we already
had a Tannaitic source for it?
That's pretty obvious. I mean, wouldn't you rather bring the source for
something that talks about סקילה skilah than all these other גזירה שוות?
gezeirah shavot? Oh, okay.
So the
גמרא Gemara
says: נאמר קאמר. ne'emar ka'amar. He already said... קאמר ka'amar what he's
saying is, what the תנא Tanna is saying, קאמר ka'amar אילו לא
נאמר ilu lo ne'emar קאמר. ka'amar. If he... if we didn't have
this more obvious verse that רב פפא Rav Pappa ends up bringing
then we would have used this... then we would have used these
גזירה שוות. gezeirah shavot. והכי קאמר vehachi ka'amar and this is what
the תנא Tanna was saying: אילו לא נאמר קרא הייתי אומר גזירה
שוה.
ilu lo ne'emar
kra hayiti omer gezeirah shavah. If the פסוק pasuk that רב פפא
Rav Pappa just brought of הוצא את המקלל אל מחוץ למחנה hotzei
et ha'mikalel el mi'chutz la'machaneh and ויוציאו את המקלל אל מחוץ למחנה,
vayotziu et ha'mikalel el mi'chutz la'machaneh, then I would have had to
use this גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. השתא דנאמר קרא גזירה שוה לא
צריך. hashta de'ne'emar kra gezeirah shavah lo tzarich. We don't need the
גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah because the... we had a more simple learning
that רב פפא Rav Pappa brought. Okay.
Yeah,
exactly.
It was all just a fun intellectual exercise in גזירה שוה. gezeirah
shavah. Thank you.
Which, by the way, this... if you're teaching גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah,
then this is probably a pretty good סוגיא sugya to teach.
Yeah. Okay, ותירן גמרא. ve'teiren Gemara. רב אשי אמר. Rav Ashi amar.
משה היכא הוה יתיב? Moshe heicha hava yativ? So רב אשי Rav
Ashi is going to bring another source for how we know...
what's רב אשי Rav Ashi going to do? רב אשי אמר Rav
Ashi amar משה היכא הוה יתיב במחנה לויה היכא יתיב? Moshe heicha
hava yativ be'machaneh Leviyah heicha yativ? Where was... where was משה רבינו
Moshe Rabbeinu sitting? במחנה לויה. be'machaneh Leviyah. He sat in the מחנה
לויה. machaneh Leviyah. ואמר ליה רחמנא הוצא את המקלל חוץ למחנה. ve'amar
lei Rachmana hotzei et ha'mikalel chutz la'machaneh. God said take out the
curser... take the curser outside of the מחנה. machaneh. Take the...
take the curser outside of the מחנה, machaneh, חוץ למחנה לויה. chutz
la'machaneh Leviyah.
Sorry, I got sidetracked.
If he was in מחנה לויה machaneh Leviyah then... if משה Moshe
is in מחנה לויה machaneh Leviyah God says הוצא. hotzei.
מחנה לוויה Machane Liviya ואמר ליה רחמנא, v'amar leh Rachmana, God says
to him, הוצא את המקלל חוץ למחנה Hotzei es hamekallel chutz laMachane
לוויה. Liviya. He says, take him outside, take him outside the מחנה
לוויה Machane Liviya אל מחוץ למחנה, el michutz lamachane, חוץ למחנה ישראל.
chutz laMachane Yisrael. So he splits the verse in two. הוציאו אותו
Hotzi'o oso is "take him out of מחנה לוויה," Machane Liviya, אל
מחוץ למחנה el michutz lamachane is "outside of מחנה ישראל." Machane Yisrael.
ויוציאו את המקלל Vayotzi'u es hamekallel לעשייה. la'asiya.
And the ויוציאו את המקלל, Vayotzi'u es hamekallel, which רב פפא Rav
Pappa used to learn that they took him all the way out
of מחנה ישראל, Machane Yisrael, רב אשי Rav Ashi uses to teach
us that that's just telling us that it actually happened. Ah, but
the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to go back to what it said about
רב פפא. Rav Pappa. עשייה בהדיא כתיב בהו ובני ישראל עשו כאשר
צוה השם את משה.
Asiya behedya kesiv behu uvenei Yisrael asu ka'asher tziva Hashem
es Moshe. It says explicitly that בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael did that
which God commanded משה. Moshe. המיבעי ליה חד
לסמיכה וחד
לדחייה.
Ha mibaye leh chad l'smicha
v'chad l'dchiya. So that we know that עשו כאשר צוה השם את
משה, asu ka'asher tziva Hashem es Moshe, we learn that they have
to do סמיכה. smicha. The people have to lay their hands on
the person who's about to be put to death before he's put
to death. I think רש"י Rashi describes it here.
Oh, it says the פסוק pasuk says וכל השומעים את ידיהם על
ראשו. v'chol hashom'im es yedeihem al rosho.
Oh, there you go. So that is to teach us that they
actually did that.
Why? I mean, like,
why two פסוקים, psukim, one for סמיכה smicha and one for דחייה,
dchiya, if God says, you know, do this, this, this, and then
it says they did it.
Right. So רש"י, Rashi, let's look at רש"י. Rashi.
It's about let's see, one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight
lines down. דיבור המתחיל המיבעי ליה Dibur Hamaschil Ha mibaye leh is
eight lines down in the narrow lines in רש"י. Rashi. המיבעי ליה
לסמיכה ולדחייה. Mibaye leh l'smicha u'l'dchiya.
You need that פסוק pasuk to teach us about סמיכה, smicha, laying
his hands, laying our hands on him, and דחייה, dchiya, pushing the
stone onto him, I believe is the דחייה. dchiya.
No, דחייה dchiya was pushing him off from a height.
Ah, yes. Sorry, you're right. Pushing him off of a cliff or
the top of a house or whatever it ends up being.
דכתיב בסמיכה וסמכו ולא
מפורש בעשייה.
Dichsiv b'smicha v'samchu v'lo
mforash b'asiya.
So דחייה dchiya is not said anywhere in the command. Right.
So I think that's where, I think that's really where this is
coming is to say that there was an extra step involved that
is not explicitly stated in the command, but בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
did anyway because later on we, I don't know the גמרא Gemara
there, but I assume that we learn from a פסוק pasuk somewhere
that this דחייה dchiya needs to happen. בסמיכה וסמכו וגו' ולא
מפורש בעשייה. B'smicha v'samchu
v'go' v'lo mforash b'asiya.
It wasn't in the
סמיכה, smicha, and it's not stated explicitly in the doing of the
סקילה. skila. הדר סיים קרא ובני ישראל עשו אף סמיכה ודחייה. Hadar
siyeim kra uvenei Yisrael asu af smicha u'dchiya. Right, they after the
גמרא, Gemara,
after the תורה Torah describes what they did, it says again ובני
ישראל עשו. uvenei Yisrael asu.
It says they took him out, they laid their hands on him,
they stoned him. How come the תורה Torah has to go back
and say that they did everything that God commanded? That means that
they did even סמיכה smicha and דחייה. dchiya. ודחייה סמיכה וסמכו כל
השומעים. U'dchiya smicha v'samchu kol hashom'im.
סמיכה Smicha they
did.
סמיכה Smicha it says explicitly וסמכו כל השומעים. v'samchu kol hashom'im. Everybody
who heard him curse laid their hands upon him. דחייה לאו הכא
כתיבא אלא מסיני הלכה למשה מסיני. Dchiya lav hacha ksiva ela misinai
Halacha l'Moshe miSinai. Oh, it's just
הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha l'Moshe miSinai.
ירה ירה Yareh yareh from הר סיני, Har Sinai, meaning because God
said it on הר סיני. Har Sinai. Just like או סקל יסקל
או ירה ירה. o sakol yisakeil o yareh yareh.
Either stoned or
shot or whatever. Right. ירה ירה Yareh yareh however you pronounce it.
מסיני ירה ירה. Misinai yareh yareh. מכאן שאחד מן העדים בא ודוחהו
ומפילו מגובה בית הסקילה. Mikan she'echad min ha'edim ba v'docho u'mapilo migova
beis haskila. And so one of the witnesses comes and pushes him
off the בית הסקילה beis haskila לארץ la'aretz down to the ground.
בית הסקילה גבוה שתי קומות. Beis haskila gavoha shtei qomos. It's two
stories high. So in other words the תורה Torah doesn't really, it's
interesting that the גמרא Gemara includes here סמיכה smicha and דחייה dchiya
because it does say סמיכה smicha explicitly. It says וסמכו. v'samchu. Right.
וסמכו כל השומעים. V'samchu kol hashom'im. It says explicitly. The דחייה dchiya
is not stated here explicitly.
So I think it's more to explain the דחייה dchiya but it
brings them together for some reason.
Right, because you could have thought this הר סיני או סקל יסקל
או ירה ירה, Har Sinai o sakol yisakeil o yareh yareh, you
should be stoned or shot at or something. But it doesn't, you
know, because they are doing it all... Right. But it doesn't mean
to shoot arrows because you know, they're saying that it's all סקילה
skila
and it means to push him off.
If he doesn't die by the ירה ירה yareh yareh which is
pushing him off.
Right. It's an interesting visual in
the on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you know, the sacrifice that goes
out and then they push it off. Right. The...
and there too, there too it's not and also putting the
hands... there too it's also not stated explicitly by the שעיר לעזאזל
se'ir l'Azazel by the goat. What's it called in English?
The scapegoat. It also doesn't say you push it off a cliff
explicitly. Oh. But the גמרא Gemara learns there
and actually interestingly the ר"ש... Rash...
רשב״א Rashba or רשב״ם Rashbam talk about how it's like a polemic
against Christians because that's a whole different topic, but the שעיר לעזאזל,
Se'ir L'Azazel, the scapegoat is in Christianity taken as a parable for
Jesus, so to push the goat off the cliff is like a
polemic against that. But again, maybe it could also be connected to
this, that יוציא, yotze, that
this strike him through with arrows, חז״ל Chazal actually mean it to
take—mean it to push him off the cliff, and so
right you have
the...
before Jesus, how are you saying that? Wait,
what?
How are you
connecting them to Jesus?
I mean you're saying the scapegoat was, you know,
much—much before Jesus' time.
But they weren't necessarily pushing it off a cliff.
Oh, you think that was something that was...
it's not—not me, it's the רשב״א Rashba or the רשב״ם, Rashbam, I
don't remember which. I didn't make the claim. Okay, wait. דהכי כתיב
והוציא את הכבשים אשר דבשא.
De-hachi
ketiv v'hotzi et hakvasim asher devasha.
אמרו ליה רבנן לרב אשי לדידך כל הני הוציא דכתיבי בפרים הנשרפים
מאי דרשת
בהו קשיא.
Amru leh Rabbanan le-Rav Ashi l'didach kol hanei hotzi d'chtivei
befarim hanisrafim mai darshta
behu kashya. So the רבנן Rabbanan say back to רב אשי, Rav
Ashi, hang on, if you're going to make that claim about
הוציא, hotzi, the word הוציא hotzi that means דחיה dechiya and whatever,
then in every case where it says הוציא hotzi you would have
to learn a דרשה drasha from it. So when in
the par—when the פרים הנשרפים parim hanisrafim it also says
הוציא, hotzi, מאי דרשת, mai darshta, what did you learn from that
word? קשיא. Kashya. The גמרא Gemara concludes that in fact it is—that's
a good קשיא kashya against רב אשי, Rav Ashi, so his דרשה
drasha is probably not accepted.
פיסקא Piska from
the
משנה: Mishnah: אחד
עומד על פתח בית דין והסודרים בידו. Echad omed al petach beit
din vehasudarim beyado. So
one person stands outside of the בית דין Beit Din and has
like flags in his hands to signal if—if someone has
a—an good appeal of the דין. din. אמר רב הונא פשיטא לי
אחד אבן שנסקל בה ואחד עץ שנתלה בו ואחד סייף שנהרג בו
ואחד סודר שנחנק בו כולן משל ציבור.
Amar Rav Huna pshita li echad even sheniskal bah ve'echad etz shenitlah
bo ve'echad sayif sheneherag bo
ve'echad sudar shenichnak bo kullan mishel tzibur. And it is obvious to
me, says רב הונא, Rav Huna, that the stone with which you
stone someone, and the tree from which you hang someone, and the
sword that people are killed with, and the scarf or the piece
of cloth that someone is strangled by, should all be—should all belong
to the ציבור, tzibur, should all be communally owned. מאי טעמא דמידי
דידיה לא אמרינן ליה זיל ואייתי ונקטול נפשך. Mai ta'ama demidi didey
lo amrinan leh zil ve'aytei veniktol nafshech. We don't say to him,
go get your stone, go get your tree, go get your scarf,
and we're going to kill you with it.
בעי רב הונא: Ba'ei Rav Huna: סודר שמניפין בו וסוס שרץ ומעמידו
משל מי? Sudar shemanifin bo vesus sheratz uma'amido mishel mi?
So the סודרין, sudarin, the cloth that you use, or the flags
that you signal, and this horse that's out there in case he
needs to run to catch up to the killing party, who do
they belong to? כיון דהצלה דידיה מדידיה הוא Keivan d'hatzalah didey mididey
hu
because they are there in order to save him from death, maybe
they should belong to him. או דלמא כיון דבית דינא מחייבין למעבד
הא הצלה מדידהו הוא O dilma keivan debeit dina mechayvin lema'avad ha
hatzalah mideidu hu
maybe because it is the בית דין Beit Din that are חייב
chayav in providing these things and need to save him if the
situation arises, it should belong to the בית דין Beit Din and
therefore be communally owned? And furthermore הכא דאמר רבי חייא בר רב
אשי אמר רב חסדא היוצא ליהרג משקין אותו קורט של לבונה.
Hacha d'amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Rav Ashi amar Rav Chisda hayotze l'hareg
mashkin oto
koret shel levonah. The person who you're bringing out to—to kill is
supposed to drink this some lavender tea?
Is that what it is?
קורט Koret is lavender.
They say frankincense.
Oh, frankincense.
Mixed into a cup of wine.
Sorry, frankincense. I don't know what either of those really are anyway.
That's not true, I do know what lavender is.
Frankincense.
קורט של לבונה. Koret shel levonah. See? I'm good at pretending to
be Rabbi Linder sometimes, right? And
that's on video.
Oh,
forgive me, another thing to atone for before Yom Kippur.
לבונה Levonah is part of the קטורת. Ketoret.
Yeah, לבונה Levonah is part of the קטורת, Ketoret, yeah.
That's the frankincense.
So you give them some frankincense mixture בכוס של יין bekos shel
yayin in a in a wine mixed with wine כדי שתטרף דעתו.
kedei shetitaref da’ato. It somehow eases his mind. Dulls his senses.
Probably addles his mind. He doesn't know what's happening.
Maybe you just get him drunk. Yes, תטרף. titaref.
Oh, that's תשתבש. tishtabesh.
You're right. כדי שתטרף. kedei shetitaref.
But why would you want him
to be, yeah, I don't want him
to feel the pain as much, you don't want him to know
really what's going on. Right.
It's let's
see,
Rashi says תטרף דעתו ולא ידאג ויתמהמה בהריגתו. titaref da'ato velo yidag
veyitmahmeha baharigato. Right, he goes crazy and he's confused so he doesn't
really know what's happening anymore. כדי שתטרף דעתו kedei shetitaref da’ato שנאמר
shenemar תנו שכר לאובד ויין למרי נפש. tnu shechar le’oved veyayin lemarei
nafesh.
Give beer to someone who is lost and wine to someone who
is bitter of spirit. So ותניא נשים יקרות שבירושלים היו מתנדבות ומביאות
אותן.
vetanya nashim yekarot shebirushalayim hayu mitnadvot
umeviot otan. The precious women of Jerusalem used to volunteer and bring
the wine, this wine and frankincense mixture of their own accord. So
the question then, right, who did we have? Rav Chisda is asking
Rav Huna, who brings it if the women don't volunteer? לא התנדבו,
lo hitnadvu, if they did not volunteer and bring it of their
own accord? לא נתנדבו נשים יקרות משל מי? lo nitnadvu nashim yekarot
mishel mi? Who should it come from? הא ודאי מסתברא משל ציבור,
ha vadai mistabra mishel tzibbur, because it says תנו, tnu, because it
says give, the command says give, or the Mishnah says, no, sorry,
the pasuk says תנו שכר, tnu shechar, right? It's a plural command,
you give, therefore it should be from the ציבור. tzibbur. מדידהו בא,
midideihu ba, from them, right? It belonged to them, meaning the ציבור.
tzibbur. Okay, another question. בעי מיניה רב אחא בר הונא מרב ששת
אמר אחד מן התלמידים יש לו ללמד עליו זכות ונשתתק מהו.
ba’ei mineih Rav Acha bar
Huna meRav Sheshet amar echad min hatalmidim yesh lo lelamed alav zechut
venishtatek mahu.
So someone, we learned in the Mishnah that if someone says, "I
have a לימוד זכות, limud zechut, I have a reason to appeal
this sentence," then you immediately go get him and you bring him
back. If it has ממש mamash to it, if it's a good
claim. But what happens if one of the students say, "I have
a good appeal," and then he goes
quiet? Rashi says
נשתתק nishtatek means נאלם, ne’elam, he forgot what he was going to
say.
It's possible also that it means that he went mute or something
like that. In any case, he got as far as saying "I
have a good appeal" and then for whatever reason he can't actually
say the appeal. What do we say? מהו מנפח? mahu menapeiach?
You
wave the flag.
Right, מנפח רב ששת בידיה, menapeiach Rav Sheshet bideih,
Rav Sheshet blew in his hand, meaning, says Rashi, כלומר רוח הוא
זה שאמרת, klomar ruach hu zeh she’amarta,
it’s you're just blowing wind. כיון דנשתתק מה הועיל, keivan denishtatek mah
ho’il, if he was quiet, if he became quiet, what purpose does
it say that he had יש לו ללמד זכות? yesh lo lelamed
zechut? אילו הכי אתית למיחש אפילו אחד בסוף העולם נמי אימא בכל
היוצאים להרג שמא יש אחד בסוף העולם שיודע לו זכות. ilu hachi
ateit lemeichash afilu echad besof ha’olam nami eima bechol hayotzim liahareg shema
yesh echad besof ha’olam sheyada lo zechut. What's the point of saying
stop
if he said "I have something to learn" if we could assume,
if that was something we were worried about, we should worry about
everybody all over the world
possibly saying "I have a לימוד זכות limud zechut on him" and
therefore he should never be able to actually be killed.
So he blew in his hand. נשתתק אפילו אחד בסוף
העולם נמי.
nishtatek afilu echad besof
ha’olam nami. If he went silent, we should be worried about everybody
around the world that might have a לימוד זכות limud zechut on
him. התם לא קאמר הכא קאמר. hatam la ka’amar hacha ka’amar. No,
we shouldn't be worried about everybody all of the world. We don't
know that everybody all over the world is saying יש לו ללמד
זכות. yesh lo lelamed zechut. In this case, he said "I have
a לימוד זכות" limud zechut and then he went silent.
מה, mah, okay, so what is the דין? din? תא שמע דאמר
רבי יוסי בר חנינא אחד מן התלמידים שזיכה ומת רואים.
ta shema de’amar Rabbi Yosi bar Chanina echad min hatalmidim shezikah
umet ro’im. רואין אותו כאילו חי ועומד במקומו. ro'in oto ke'ilu chai
v'omed bimkomo.
So רבי יוסי בר חנינא Rabbi Yosi bar Chanina brings a solution
or the גמרא Gemara brings a possible solution to this question. One
of the תלמידים talmidim was זיכה. zika. We're going to the גמרא
Gemara is going to question what that means whether it means I
have a לימוד זכות limud zechut or it means I have a
לימוד זכות limud zechut and this is what it is blah blah
blah and he actually finished it and then he died. רואין אותו
כאילו חי. ro'in oto ke'ilu chai. We see him as if he
is alive and we put someone else in his place for the
vote of whether or not he's חייב מיתה chayav mita or not.
Oh there's a good there's a very interesting censored גמרא. Gemara. I
don't know if you have that. Like this version has...
Oh no I don't have...
Right there's an extended there's a whole thing here about Jesus being
killed.
Oh no I don't have this.
This is the third Jesus. So you know if you wanted at
some point...
Okay. What printing is
this?
It's really explicitly about Jesus. So you might want to share that
with me later.
All right we'll see if we have... Right because the גמרא Gemara
later on in this page the גמרא Gemara at
the end of this page is very clearly cut off and we
don't well we'll get there. Okay. שזיכה ומת רואין אותו כאילו חי.
shezika u'meit ro'in oto ke'ilu chai. We see him as if he's
alive and you put someone else in his place in order to
vote for him. זיכה אין לא זיכה לא. zika in lo zika
lo. So if he finished his לימוד זכות limud zechut then you
do put someone in this place
and if he didn't
finish his לימוד זכות limud zechut then you don't. Meaning that if
someone said יש לי ללמד זכות yesh li l'lamed zechut and he
didn't say anything more we should ignore him. It doesn't count for
anything. זיכה פשיטא לי אמר תיבעי לך. zika peshita li amar tiba'i
lach. It is obvious that if he finished his לימוד זכות limud
zechut then you put someone in his place but if he did
not אמר amar if he just said יש לי ללמד זכות yesh
li l'lamed zechut תיבעי לך tiba'i lach that is the question. And
this is where the גמרא Gemara is very clearly cut off and
you have a whole thing. Boy I don't... Let's keep going in
our printed version. If we have time we'll come back and try
to learn this because I haven't I haven't actually seen it. All
I saw was that it's cut off here.
What's the difference between what is this here that has that in
it?
It's just a printing that includes the censored parts. I
see. It seems like רש"י Rashi here also
רש"י Rashi also had a censored version or רש"י Rashi was also
censored.
It's actually quite a bit of גמרא Gemara there.
I'm glad there's less because then we're then we might be able
to get through it. Okay. אפילו הוא וכו' afillu hu v'chulei says
the משנה mishnah said... Sorry. אפילו הוא. afillu hu. והסוס רץ ועומדים
ואפילו הוא אומר יש לי ללמד על עצמי זכות מחזירין אותו.
v'hasus ratz v'omedim v'afillu hu omer yesh li l'lamed
al atzmi zechut machzirin oto. Even if he says I
have a reason to appeal my
sentence even he can say that. And it... דאפילו d'afillu so the
גמרא Gemara learns דאפילו. d'afillu. It says דאפילו d'afillu right? Even him.
פעם ראשונה ושנייה. pa'am rishona u'shniya. Does that happen as many times
as he wants? He can go out and say I have I
have an appeal for my sentence? והתניא? v'ha tanya? But we have
a ברייתא. braita. פעם ראשונה ושנייה בין שיש ממש בדבריו בין שאין
ממש בדבריו מחזירין אותו. pa'am rishona u'shniya bein sheyesh mamash bidvarav bein
she'ein mamash bidvarav machzirin oto. Whether it is the first time or
the second time if there's actual ממשות mamashut to what he says
if there is substance thank you to what he's saying then you
do bring him back. I'm sorry. Whether or not there is substance
to his claim you bring him back. מכאן ואילך אם יש ממש
בדבריו מחזירין אותו. mikan v'eilach im yesh mamash bidvarav machzirin oto. If
there's substance to what he's saying you bring him back and you
retry him. אין ממש בדבריו אין מחזירין אותו. ein mamash bidvarav ein
machzirin oto. If there's no if there's no substance to what he's
saying then you do not bring him back. אמר רב פפא Amar
Rav Papa תרגמוה מפעם שנייה ואילך. targumuha mipa'am shniya v'eilach. We're talking
about in our... Right because the משנה mishnah said ואפילו הוא אומר
יש לי ללמד על עצמי זכות מחזירין אותו אפילו ארבע וחמש פעמים
ובלבד שיש ממש בדבריו.
v'afillu hu omer yesh li
l'lamed al atzmi zechut machzirin oto afillu arba v'chamesh pe'amim u'bilvad sheyesh
mamash bidvarav. You bring him back four or even five times but
that's only if there's ממש בדבריו. mamash bidvarav. But our ברייתא braita
just said even if there's no even if there's no substance to
what he's saying you bring him back the first and second time.
תרגמוה: targumuha: explain this משנה mishnah as meaning from the second time
onward meaning from the third time onward after the second time our
משנה mishnah is talking about. מנא ידעי? mena yad'ei? How do we
know that there's ממשות mamashut to what he's saying? How do we
know there's substance? אמר אביי דמסרינן ליה זוגא דרבנן. amar Abaye d'masrinan
lei zuga d'rabanan. A pair of rabbis go along with him to
hear his claims. אי איכא ממש בדבריו אין אי לא לא. ei
ika mamash bidvarav in ei lo lo. And they know and they
hear if there's substance to what he's saying and they bring him
back or they don't. ולמסר ליה מעיקרא? v'limsar lei me'ikara? Why not
the first and second time also send rabbis and find out if
there's substance to what he's saying? אגב דבעית ליה. agav d'ba'it lei.
Because he's afraid he might not actually be able to say everything
that he wants to say and fully complete his claims. Therefore, the
first and second time, we allow him to come back, even if
there's no substance to his claims. Okay. New משנה Mishnah with a
short גמרא Gemara following. מצאו לו זכות פטרוהו ואם לאו יצא ליסקל.
Matzu lo zchut pat'ruhu v'im lav yetzei l'isakel. If you find, if
someone, so we're talking about after, going back to the previous משנה,
Mishnah,
you brought him out,
someone was מלמד זכות melamed zchut
on him and you bring him back. If there's a good claim
to make that he is not actually חייב מיתה, chayav mita, then
he's פטור. patur. ואם לאו יצא ליסקל, V'im lav yetzei l'isakel, you
bring him back out and you go through the whole thing again.
וכרוז יוצא לפניו V'charoz yotzei l'fanav and an announcer goes out in
front of him. איש פלוני בן פלוני יוצא ליסקל,
Ish ploni ben ploni
yotzei l'isakel, Joe Schmo is going
out to be stoned על שעבר עבירה
פלוני al she'avar aveira ploni that he did such and such an
עבירה, aveira, ופלוני ופלוני עדיו u'ploni u'ploni edav and so and so
and so and so are the witnesses. כל מי שיודע לו זכות,
Kol mi sheyodeia lo zchut, anybody who knows a לימוד זכות limud
zchut on him, יבוא וילמד עליו, yavo v'yelamed alav, anybody who knows
a לימוד זכות, limud zchut, you should come and say it so
that if he doesn't deserve to be put to death, he won't
be. גמרא. Gemara. אמר אביי וצריך למימר ביום פלוני ובשעה פלוני ובמקום
פלוני דלמא איכא דדעו ואתו ומזמינו ליה.
Amar Abaye v'tzarich l'meimar b'yom ploni u'v'sha'ah
ploni u'v'makom ploni dilma ika did'u v'atu u'mazmim leh. The announcer also
has to say and it happened on such and such a day,
at such and such a time, in such and such a place,
so that if anybody knows that the witnesses who were announced were
not actually at that place and time, then they can come and
ומזמינו u'mazmim the witnesses, they can come and make them עדים זוממין,
edim zomemin, lying, lying witnesses. Okay. וכרוז יוצא לפניו, V'charoz yotzei l'fanav,
an announcer goes out in front of him. לפניו אין מעיקרא לא?
L'fanav in mei'ikara lo? Oh, this is another place, no, sorry, I
think this is the place where it's cut off. Oh, this is
this is this is cut off but I don't think it's censored
here. מכאן עד סוף העמוד הושמט על ידי הצנזורה ונוסף כאן על
פי הויניציה. Mikan ad sof ha'amud hushmat al yad ha'tzensura v'nosaf kan
al pi ha-Venetzia. So this version, where's the... you don't see the
הש"ס דפורצקי? Hashas d'Poretsky? Right, it's cut off here but this doesn't
seem to indicate... והתניא בערב הפסח תלוהו לישו. v'ha tanya b'erev ha-pesach
taluhu l'Yeshu. Oh, no, yeah, so this is where the censor, this
is where the censor got his hands on it. לפניו אין מעיקרא
לא? L'fanav in mei'ikara lo? Which right, there's usually a question. He
goes out to announce in front of him? Yes. But מעיקרא, mei'ikara,
from the beginning of the trial, no? Did he not go out?
Does a person not go out and announce? Right? Which makes sense.
Why would you send out an announcer right before he's being killed
and not from the beginning of the trial to try to find
more witnesses if they know how to be ומזמינו u'mazmim the current
witnesses? And this is where the censor is, and just the ברייתא,
Braita, the גמרא Gemara goes on here and says והתניא, v'ha tanya,
but we have the following ברייתא: Braita: בערב הפסח תלוהו לישו. B'erev
ha-Pesach taluhu l'Yeshu. They hung Jesus on ערב פסח. Erev Pesach. And
it goes on, but if we have time we'll get back to
it. Wait, isn't the reason why it doesn't go out according to
the words of the משנה Mishnah is because they specifically say that
he's going to be taken out to be stoned? So the judgment
has already have been made? Right. You're saying, you know, why don't
they say it at the beginning of the trial? So then you'd
have to reword this... Reword what? The גמרא's Gemara saying לפניו אין
מעיקרא לא. l'fanav in mei'ikara lo. Not the... I'm sorry, the משנה.
Mishnah. In other words, the משנה's Mishnah already saying that he is
being taken out to be stoned, he has transgressed, so that means
the judgment, the verdict has already been made. Right, and the גמרא's
Gemara asking... you're suggesting that they've announced this before... so they'd have
to rephrase... That's what the גמרא's Gemara asking. The גמרא's Gemara asking
לפניו אין, l'fanav in, this announcer goes out in front of him?
Yes. מעיקרא, mei'ikara, from the beginning, of the beginning of the דין,
din, he does not go out and announce it? Right. And the
גמרא's Gemara asking how come not? And then it doesn't answer the
question because it was censored. Oh I see. Okay. אמר רבי יהושע
בן לוי. Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי:
Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi: כל הזובח את יצרו ומתודה עליו מעלה
עליו הכתוב כאילו כבדו להקדוש ברוך הוא בשני עולמים. Kol hazove'ach et
yitzro u'mitvadeh alav ma'aleh alav ha-katuv k'ilu kibdu l'Hakadosh Baruch Hu b'shnei
olamim. Anybody who sacrifices his יצר הרע yetzer hara and admits what
he did, he confesses his sin. The מעלה ma'aleh עליו alav הכתוב,
hakatuv, the verse is said about him as if he honored God
in two worlds, this world and the world to come. דכתיב dichtiv
זובח zove'ach תודה toda יכבדנני, yachabdaneni, that someone who sacrifices a תודה,
toda, in this case it means a תודה toda sacrifice in the
פסוק, pasuk, יכבדנני yachabdaneni honors me. תודה toda is from the same
שורש shoresh as מתודה, mitvadeh, which I didn't realize until I learned
this גמרא Gemara and that's an interesting connection that I think giving
thanks and confess are from the same שורש shoresh from the same
root, which is there's a lot to discuss there but we're not
going to. יכבדנני yachabdaneni and the fact that there are two נונים
nunin in this word יכבדנני, yachabdaneni, usually it would just be יכבדני.
yachabdani. There are two נונים nunin meaning one נון nun for עולם
olam הזה, hazeh, one נון nun for עולם olam הבא. haba. ואמר
ve'amar רבי Rabbi יהושע Yehoshua בן ben לוי, Levi, בזמן bizman שבית
she'Beit המקדש haMikdash קיים, kayam, אדם adam מקריב makriv עולה, olah, שכר
schar עולה olah בידו, beyado, מנחה, minchah, שכר schar מנחה minchah בידו.
beyado. When the בית Beit המקדש haMikdash is standing, someone who brings
these two different קרבנות, korbanot, an עולה olah and a מנחה, minchah,
he gets rewarded because he brought those. אבל aval מי mi שדעתו
sheda'ato שפלה, shiflah, שפלה, shiflah, someone whose דעת da'at is שפלה, shiflah,
I think רש"י Rashi said, nope, what does Artscroll say שפלה shiflah
is here? I forgot. Sorry. What's that? Oh right. He makes his
he makes his mind lowly so that he can, right, that's like
how you do how you confess. You make your mind low and
you because you're human and you're and you're a sinner. Anybody who
makes his דעתו da'ato low, anybody lowers his mind, מעלה ma'aleh עליו
alav הכתוב, hakatuv, the verse is written about him כאילו ke'ilu הקריב
hikriv כל kol הקרבנות hakorbanot כולן, kulan, as if he made all
of the sacrifices כל kol הקרבנות hakorbanot כולן, kulan, שנאמר shenemar זבחי
zivchei אלהים Elohim רוח ruach נשברה. nishbarah. The the verse says it
does this דרשה drashah on the פסוק, pasuk, the sacrifices of God
are of a broken soul, of a broken soul or spirit. ולא
velo עוד od אלא ela שאין she'ein תפלתו tefilato נמאסת, nim'eset, and
the person who makes his mind lowly his prayer is not rejected
שנאמר shenemar לב lev נשבר nishbar ונדכה venidkeh אלהים Elohim לא lo
תבזה. tivzeh. It does the דרשה drashah on that פסוק pasuk also
that your prayer is not rejected. Okay. Next משנה. Mishnah. היה hayah
רחוק rachok מבית mi'beit הסקילה ha'skilah כעשר ke'eser אמות amot אומרים לו
omrim lo התוודה, hitvadeh, שכן sheken דרך derech כל kol המומתין hamumatin
מתוודים, mitvadin, שכל shekol המתוודה hamitvadeh יש yesh לו lo חלק chelek
לעולם הבא, l'olam haba שכן sheken מצינו matzinu בעכן be'Achan שאמר she'amar
לו lo יהושע Yehoshua בני beni שים sim נא na כבוד kavod
להשם la'Hashem אלהי Elohei ישראל Yisrael ותן viten לו lo תודה. toda.
והיאך, sorry I'll go back translate. So once he is ten אמות
amot about כעשר, ke'eser, when he's about ten אמות from the בית
Beit הסקילה, ha'skilah, which is close enough to see where you're about
to be pushed off and put to death, they say to him
confess your sins for it is the way of anybody who's about
to be put to death that they should confess their sins, because
anybody who confesses his sins, he has a place in the world
to come. It's interesting to juxtapose this with the tenth פרק perek
where it says כל kol ישראל Yisrael יש yesh להם lahem חלק
chelek לעולם le'Olam הבא Haba, except for certain people and I don't
believe that someone who is put to death without confessing is included
in that list. So anybody who confesses his sins, he has a
place in the world to come, for that's what we find in
עכן. Achan. עכן Achan sinned against God by taking property that was
supposed to be completely burned or possibly set, no, he did מעילה.
me'ilah. The בני Bnei ישראל Yisrael swear that they're going to honor
God after they after they conquer certain cities by by consecrating all
of the property and עכן Achan takes some of it for his
own, which is מעילה, me'ilah, which is taking consecrated property without permission
to use for non-holy purposes. This is also like the וידוי Vidui
why any person who's about to die says the וידוי, Vidui, right?
Right, right, right. כל kol המומתין hamumatin doesn't just doesn't just mean
someone who's about to be put to death, it means anybody who's
about to die, which is why we also do וידוי Vidui on
our deathbed. That's right. For יהושע Yehoshua says to him בני beni
שים sim נא na כבוד kavod please before עכן Achan is about
right before עכן Achan is about to be put to death, יהושע
Yehoshua says to him give give honor to God, the God of
ישראל, Yisrael, and confess. ויען vaya'an עכן Achan את et יהושע Yehoshua
ויאמר vayomar אמנה omnah אנכי anochi חטאתי chatati וכזאת vechazot וכזאת vechazot
וגו' vechulu and he says I have sinned. actually actually worked and
he was and he was forgiven? שנאמר Shene'emar ויאמר יהושע מה עכרתנו
יעכרך ה' ביום הזה. Vayomer Yehoshua meh achartanu ya'acharcha Hashem bayom hazeh.
ביום הזה אתה עכור ואי אתה עכור לעולם הבא. Bayom hazeh ata
achur v'ee ata achur l'olam haba. Oh, I don't remember what that
means at all. What is עכור? achur? Like murky water. Right, it's
also, right. Not עכור, achur, like to be ruined, it seems to
be. Displaced, yes, like murky, be ruined. It's not clear, not clean.
Not that the word, not that the meaning is not clear. The
meaning of the word is is not clear. Dirty, right? Something messy.
Right. Okay. So, in the world to come, but in the right,
so ביום, bayom, right, it says ביום הזה יעכרך ה'. bayom hazeh
ya'acharcha Hashem. God is God makes you dirty today, I guess would
be the maybe what it means. God makes you dirty today, ביום
הזה אתה עכור. bayom hazeh ata achur. Today you are filthy, unclean,
ואי אתה עכור לעולם הבא. v'ee ata achur l'olam haba. But לעולם
le'Olam הבא Haba you are you are clean because your sins have
been forgiven. ומי שאינו יודע להתוודות U'mi she'eino yodeya l'hitvadot and if
he does not know how to confess אומרים omrim לו lo אמור
תהא מיתתי כפרה על כל עונותי. emor tehei mitati kapara al kol
avonotai. You and if he doesn't know how to confess they say
just say let my death be serve as atonement for all of
my sins. And you know like זך zach is also to be
pure, so עכור achur is like to be dirty, so it can
be like the opposite of זך. zach. Like לזכות lizkot is related
to clear, clear something. Nice. So that's the עכור achur is that
it's murky, it's not clear. It's the opposite of זכות. zchut. It's
not gonna work, but in the next right, it's not dirty like,
it's dirty as in the opposite of זכות, zchut, right? Because זכות
zchut throughout all of this means יש לו עליו זכות, yesh lo
alav zchut, like the opposite of זך. zach. I like that. Okay.
אמור תהא מיתתי כפרה על כל עונותי. Amor tehei mitati kapara al
kol avonotai. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer אם היה יודע שהוא
מזומם im haya yodeya shehu mezumam if this person knows that he
did not sin אמור תהא מיתתי כפרה על כל עונותי emor tehei
mitati kapara al kol avonotai חוץ מעון זה. chutz me'avon zeh. If
the person knows that he is is wow, what's what's not guilty?
If he if he knows he's not guilty, he says let my
death serve as כפרה kapara for all of my sins except for
this transgression. אמרו לו Amru lo the רבנן Rabbanan said back to
him. I just gotta say the parallel
I was making before with יום כיפור Yom Kippur also here. They
say יום כיפור Yom Kippur
atones and death atones.
Right. Right. יום כיפור Yom Kippur and death, yeah. But what's interesting
is on יום כיפור Yom Kippur we confess sins we confess every
sin regardless of
whether or not we did it, whereas here you're saying, here this
person's saying, what's that? Sins we
didn't
do?
אשמנו בגדנו גזלנו דיברנו דופי.
Ashamnu bagadnu
gazalnu dibarnu dofi.
We didn't necessarily do those things. I didn't, I don't know. Sure
there are things on that list you didn't do this year. Okay.
But I'm thinking of this as a communal list, not as a
personal list. Certainly, but even so, it is it works both ways
like you're including your still including yourself I I don't know. Maybe
you're right. It is a communal list because it's plural. It's in
the plural.
So that's a
whole other question
of how come how we're doing, but it's a whole different kind
of confession than what's happening here. Okay. אמרו לו Amru lo
the רבנן Rabbanan said back
to him, אם כן יהו כל אדם אומר כן כדי לנקות עצמו.
im kein yehu kol adam omer kein
kidei l'nakot atzmo. Everybody's gonna
say that thing in
order to clean himself so that people after he dies will assume
that he did not actually do this crime. Which is an interesting
statement by the רבנים Rabbanim about an individual who's about to go
be put to death, what his where his faith is at that
moment, because if רבנן Rabbanan are saying that death atones for your
sins and you know that you've done this sin, but they're assuming
that someone who did this sin is going to say I didn't,
let my death forgive me for all of my sins, let my
death be atonement for all of my sins except for this one,
but he knows he did it, then he he clearly doesn't actually
there's something in him that doesn't believe either he believes that death
is going to atone for his sins anyway or he cares more
about his reputation... Does that make sense? חזל Chazal are saying, if
you confess your sins before you
die, your death will be atonement for you. רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda comes along and says, if he knows he didn't
do this sin, he should say, let my death forgive me for
all of my sins, except for this one. And then the רבנן
Rabbanan come back and say, everybody's going to say that. Right. But
if רבנן Rabbanan are saying, if you atone for your sins, then
death, if you admit your sins and death atones for those sins,
and they assume that everybody is going to deny that they did
this thing that they're being put to death for, what does that
say about their assumptions about the people, which is to say, they
assume that people care more about their reputations in this world than
death being כפרה, kappara, death being atonement for their sins, because they're
going to assume that people are just going to deny that they
did it. I'm reading this completely different. I'm reading this as a
case of a person who is truly innocent who is being put
to death. Like this is a wrongful conviction. That's רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is saying. But the רבנן
Rabbanan come back and say, right, everybody's going to say that.